Guide to the Williams Ampère collection, circa 1793-2005.
Williams, L. Pearce, Ampère Collection
- Carton 36 (non-classes) and Carton 14 Chapter 15- Notes on classification of sciences, 1826 (Box 13, Folder 28)
- Electrical Papers- Peripheral (Box 13, Folder 29)
- Carton 10, Chapter 10, Chem 205- fragment of a memoir on magnetism (Box 13, Folder 30)
- Science Observed- Perspectives on the Social Study of Science- Knorr-Centina and Mulkay (Box 13, Folder 31)
- Many different copies of 'Exposé Méthodique des Phénomènes Electro-dynamiques', 1822-23 (Box 13, Folder 32)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 59- Action de la terre Mémoire, Oct. 1820 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 158- Action de deux éléments de courant, Oct. 1820 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 158 (potential 156) - Conclusions, Sept. 1820 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 156- Summaries of reports by Ampère on Electromagnetism, Sept. 1820 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Sur les expériences de la Rive (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 164- Expériences précies sur les attractions, Dec 26, 1820 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Reference for Ampère (Box 14, Folder 7)
- On Ampère (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Various Ampère references, 1815-1831 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Ampère's Induction Experiment (Geneva), 1822 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Ampère on Philosophy (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Bibliographie de la France ou Journal Général de L'Imprimerie et de la Librairie, Misc. Articles, 1819 (Box 14, Folder 12)
- Apercu et Mélanges (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Ampère's Bibliography on the French Book Catalogue (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Ampère's Bibliographiy (De Lavnay) (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Index of Ampère's Manuscripts (first microfilm request) (Box 14, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous Articles by Ampère (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Inspector's General- Ampère (Box 14, Folder 18)
- Inspector of Studies- Ampère, 1814 (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Inspector General of Education- Ampère, 1824-30 (Box 14, Folder 20)
- Article by Avagadro and Ampère (Box 14, Folder 21)
- Research on Fundamental Principles of Mechanics (Box 14, Folder 22)
- Article and Corrections by Ampère (see 603 for possible reference (Box 14, Folder 23)
- Carton 10 Chapter 10 Chem 190- Manuscripts on Theorem of Electrodynamics (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Index of Files and Location Information (Box 14, Folder 25)
- Archives to be checked (see microfilm) (Box 14, Folder 26)
- Ampère et Maine de Biran, 1907 (Box 14, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous Published/Unpublished Works (Box 14, Folder 28)
- Ampère et Maine de Biran (secondary sources) (Box 14, Folder 29)
- Important: Incomplete Ampère Collection (Box 14, Folder 30)
- Bonnet and Senebier Manuscripts, late 1700s (Box 14, Folder 31)
- Missing works: Démonstration de la relation découverte par Mariotte... -Ampère (Box 14, Folder 32)
- Note by Ampère on Heat and Light (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Extraits and References- Ampère (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Ampère Arts- Varied (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Tricker on Ampère (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Ampère Bibliography- Hofmann (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Ampère to Inspector General, 1834 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- File on: Maine de Biran, Degerando, Ballanche, de Jussieu, and other friends of Ampère (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Ampère- obscure sources (Important for electrodynamics) (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Interrogation of Ampère, 1793 (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous Ampère photocopies (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Why Ampère did not discover electromagnetic induction (proof by another) (Box 15, Folder 11)
- Elements of Chemical Philosophy- Ampère (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Action Mutuelle de Deux Courants- Ampère (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Physics Journal- Contents and non-physicists- Williams (Box 15, Folder 14)
- Hypnotism and Mesmerism (Box 15, Folder 15)
- Taxonomy (Box 15, Folder 16)
- Additional Manuscripts (Box 15, Folder 17)
- Correspondence: Ampère to American Philosophical Society (Box 15, Folder 18)
- Classification- Ampère (Box 15, Folder 19)
- Précis de la Théorie- Ampère, 1824 (Box 15, Folder 20)
- Notices- Ampère (Box 15, Folder 21)
- Notes on Electromagnetic Experiments- Ampère, Biot, Oersted, and Arago (Box 15, Folder 22)
- La Réfraction de la Lumière- Ampère, 1815 (Box 15, Folder 23)
- La Réfraction de la Lumière- Ampère, 1815 (Box 15, Folder 24)
- Carton 3 Chapter 3 Chem 51- Research on polygons, 1815 (Box 15, Folder 24)
- Letters- Arago and Biot by Carnot (Box 15, Folder 25)
- Physics Journal- Note (Box 15, Folder 26)
- Ampère and Kant on Philosophy, 1815 (Box 15, Folder 27)
- Mémoire de Ampère (multiple), 1821-23 (Box 15, Folder 28)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 166- Papiers de Ampère, 1815 (Box 15, Folder 29)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 162- Brouillon (Box 15, Folder 30)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 161- Electrodynamic Effects ('d'une helice en fer'), 1820 (Box 15, Folder 31)
- Carton 8 Chapter 10 Chem 16- Meeting from November 6 on attraction and repulsion, 1820 (Box 15, Folder 32)
- Maine de Biran and Ampère (Box 15, Folder 33)
- Maine de Biran (large file) (Box 15, Folder 34)
- Article on Ampère regarding Electrodynamics, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 35)
- Ampère's Secondary Biography, 1836 (Box 15, Folder 36)
- Sur les effets de l'explosion électrique sure l'aiguille aimantée'- Orsted, 1820 (Box 15, Folder 37)
- More modern accounts of Ampère's work (Box 15, Folder 38)
- Photocopy (by Williams) of a miscellaneous manuscript of Ampère (Box 15, Folder 39)
- File of locations of additional (missing) Ampère information (Box 15, Folder 40)
- Notes by Ampère on various topics (Box 15, Folder 41)
- Documents on (early parts) of Ampère's career (Box 15, Folder 42)
- Various documents: notes, proofs, etc. (Box 15, Folder 43)
- Ampère and Lycee de Lyon- appointments to Ec. Polytechnic and relations with Damouvon, 1803 (Box 15, Folder 44)
- Merleau- Ponty on Ampère (Box 15, Folder 45)
- 'Very important' proofs and notes on elementary calculus- Ampère (Box 15, Folder 46)
- Fragments of two letters: the origins of electrodynamics and the nature of the vertebrate skeleton (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Cornell Bibliography, 1819 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Cornell Bibliography, 1821 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Cornell Bibliography, 1823 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Cornell Bibliography, 1824 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Modern representation of Ampère's excerpt on magnetic repulsion (Box 16, Folder 6)
- History lectures citing Ampère; Mémoire par Ampère, 1820 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Background information and various notes (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous unidentified manuscripts (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Carton 10 Chapter 10 Chem 203- Fluides Igniformes (peripheral articles, check against Ampère's readings) (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Chemistry- Chem 249- Brouillous (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Carton 17 Chapter 16 Chem 271- Elémens de psycologie, 1807 (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Mémoire, Presenté à l'Académie, Oct 1820 (Box 16, Folder 13)
- Notes from Ampère's meetings for use at modern American meetings regarding similar topics, O (Box 16, Folder 14)
- Miscellaneous documentation- facts, proofs, and conclusions (Box 16, Folder 15)
- Ampère Publications, Brouillon, and on Paleontology (Box 16, Folder 16)
- "Important- Miscellaneous Mémoires to read" (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Ampère manuscripts from Thompson Library (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Modern articles- Sudduth, Siegfried and Dobbs citing Ampère, and by Ampère himself (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Carton 10 Chapter 10 Chem 203- Early electromagnetism (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Course on Mechanics Analysis- Ec. Polytechnic, 1823-24 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Manuscripts of Ampère and Maine de Biran (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Ampère- National Archives (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Les mots et les choses- Greene (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Misc. Ampère mss., large size- "to be reduced" for Williams' perusal (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Various bulletins and pamphlet collections by Ampère- includes relevant photographs as well (Box 18)
- Ampère titles at Cornell University Library (notes and printouts) (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Index of Williams's files (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Monographies (works by Ampère, printout from the Bibliothèque nationale de France); List of Ampère photocopies and separate publications (Box 19, Folder 3)
- "Ampère Collection: Works by Ampère that I own" (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Monographies (works by Ampère, printout from the Bibliothèque nationale de France); List of Ampère photocopies and separate publications (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Correspondence between Ampère and Maine de Biran and others, circa 1810-1817 (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Manuscripts of Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire (drafts with corrections); letter from Chevreul (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Letters to Ampère from Jan Hendrik van Swinden, Molard, and Celle, Letters from Molard and Celle are photocopies; see Information for users (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Letters from Justus Liebig, Charles Friedel, Lalande, and Ernst Wilhelm von Brucke; genealogy of Liebig, circa 1794/95-1872 (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Photographs of manuscripts etc. (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Microfilm of Karl Hullmann, Das Grundgesetz der Materie (1863); Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph von Schelling, Zeitschrift fur spekulative Physik (1800-1801); works by Francois-Vincent Raspail and Emile Saigey; and other unidentified microfilms, probably including Ampère material (Box 20-21)